Today's daf is
קלט Kuf Lamed Tet 139 and we pick up second line from
the top and we are in the middle of a little אגדתא
Aggadata because we've been talking about making an אהל Ohel but we
said that we'd digress with רמי בר יחזקאל Rami bar Yehezkel and
the whole discussion that eventually the תורה Torah will be forgotten from
Israel. So we pick up with the following.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא רבי יוסי בן אלישע
אומר אם ראית דור שצרות רבות באות עליו צא ובדוק בדייני ישראל.
Tanya Rabbi Yose ben Elisha omer, im ra'ita dor she'tzarot rabot ba'ot
alav, tze'i u'vdok b'dayanei Yisrael. If you see generations that has many
fortunes coming to
it, check of the judges of Israel, the leaders.
Rivka, today you're going to be very interested. Okay, not just now.
There's a lot of stuff coming. The leaders of Israel, the judges,
they, those are the ones that have the brunt of the responsibility.
שכל פורעניות שבאה לעולם לא באה אלא בשביל דייני ישראל. Shekol puraniyot
she'ba'ah l'olam lo ba'ah ela bishvil dayanei Yisrael. All afflictions that come
to the world
only come because of the judges of Israel. שנאמר, Shene'emar, and it
says דיינים Dayanim by the way, specifically judges, as opposed to like,
you know, leaders or whatever. שנאמר, Shene'emar, yeah, but people that are,
well, let's take a look. שמעו נא זאת ראשי בית יעקב וקציני
בית ישראל המתעבים משפט ואת כל הישרה יעקשו. Shimu na zot rashei
beit yaakov u'ktzinei beit yisrael hamita'avim mishpat v'et kol hayeshara ye'akeshuv. Hear
this the heads of בית יעקב Beit Yaakov and the leaders of
the house of
ישראל Israel who despise justice
that everything straight they will pervert. בונה ציון בדמים וירושלים בעולה. Boneh
tziyon b'damim v'yerushalayim b'avla. Build ציון Tziyon in blood, ירושלים Yerushalayim in
iniquity. ראשיה בשוחד ישפוטו וכהניה במחיר יורו. Rosheha b'shochad yishpotu v'chohaneha b'machir
yoru. Its leaders will judge through bribery
and the כהנים Kohanim will rule or will, you know, sort of
actually teach through by pay, you know, through being, you know, their
teachings can be bought. By the way, it's worth noting that the
כהנים Kohanim in this פסוק Pasuk are really like the forerunners. I
mean, the תורה, Torah, the כהנים Kohanim are the forerunners of the
Rabbis. You know, the כהנים Kohanim are יורו משפטיך ליעקב. Yoru mishpatecha
l'Yaakov. And here it's echoing the idea of יורו. Yoru. So they
were the ones who were seen as the people that would teach
תורה Torah and also the ones that would often be the ones
also that you go to for legal rulings, right? It says ובאת
אל הכהנים ואל השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם. U'vata el hakohanim v'el
hashofet asher yihyeh bayamim hahem. So anyway, here you have the judges
and the כהנים. Kohanim. But the כהנים Kohanim should be understood are
in their capacity not as those operating in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. ונביאיה בכסף יקסומו U'nevi'eha b'kesef yichsomu and its prophets with money
will literally like do magic, but you know, they're also there for,
everybody is for sale. ועל ה׳ ישענו V'al Hashem yisha'enu and they
will rely on ה׳, Hashem, meaning in the end of the פסוק
Pasuk saying, "Oh, God is with us." So basically, you know, they
have this type of a religious self-satisfaction and here they are and
they're perverting right and left and everything is for a price. Okay,
so
רשעים, Resha'im, now the גמרא Gemara comments it says they are wicked.
אלא שתלו בטחונם במי שאמר והיה העולם. Ela she'talu bitchonam b'mi she'amar
v'hayah ha'olam. But they, you know, put their faith in the one
who says and created the world. Now that could mean, that could
be a, that could be like a further condemnation or it could
be trying to, you know, to soften it to some degree. It
says okay, they're totally wicked but at least they believe in God.
You know, or it could be the, you know, the simple sense
of the פסוק Pasuk seems to be making it worse. Here they
are, they're so wicked and they still think that God is with
them. It's a good deal, Rabbi. Right, right. So anyway, so okay.
לפיכך, L'fikach, and therefore, now again, this לפיכך L'fikach because of their,
because of their iniquity alone, or is it also because of their
iniquity joined with their religious self-satisfaction and with the sense that, you
know, as if God is approving of this, which actually makes it
then even worse? So anyway, it's not clear from the way the
גמרא Gemara is phrasing it. לפיכך, L'fikach, but therefore, maybe הקדוש ברוך
הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu brings ג׳ פורעניות כנגד ג׳ עבירות שבידם. Gimel
puraniyot keneged gimel aveirot she'beyadam. God brings
three afflictions for the three sins in their hands. The three sins
were רש״י Rashi said is basically the דיינים, Dayanim, the כהנים, Kohanim,
and the נביאים. Nevi'im. Okay, so,
so what are the three afflictions? שנאמר, Shene'emar, the verse says, לכן
בגללכם ציון שדה תחרש Lachem biglalchem Tziyon sadeh techareth because of you
ציון Tziyon will be plowed like a field, וירושלים עיין תהיה Yerushalayim
iyin tihyeh and ירושלים Yerushalayim will be a, how do they translate
that? Wasteland? Something like that. והר הבית לבמות יער V'har habayit l'bamot
yaar and the, and the, and the heavenly mount will be for
a, you know, for like a river, a forest. So ואין הקדוש
ברוך הוא, V'ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so basically Jerusalem will be destroyed.
ואין הקדוש ברוך הוא משרה שכינתו על ישראל עד שיכלו שופטים ושוטרים
רעים מישראל.
V'ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mashrei shechinato al Yisrael ad she'yichlu shoftim v'shotrim
ra'im mi'Yisrael. And God will never again, will never again presumably or
never in the past, but certainly never again cause His, His שכינה
Shechinah to dwell in Israel until all of these equal evil judges
and, and officers have been destroyed. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says,
have ceased. שנאמר ואשיבה ידי עליך ואצרוף כבר סיגיך, Shene'emar v'ashiva yadi
alayich v'etzrof kabor sigayich, I will return My hand to you and
I will cleanse you like with lye, right, your, your impurities, ואסירה
כל בדיליך V'asira kol bidilayich and I will remove all of your
also like dross, ואשיבה שופטיך כבראשונה V'ashiva shoftayich k'varishona and I will
return your judges. as they were originally, your advisors as they were
in the beginning, and then it says ואחרי כן יקרא לך עיר
הצדק v'acharei khen yikarei lach ir hatzedek what's the end of the
פסוק? pasuk? ציון Tzion what is it? ואחרי כן יקרא לך עיר
הצדק. v'acharei khen yikarei lach ir hatzedek. רש"י Rashi doesn't have the
very end of the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway then afterwards you will be
considered a righteous city. So basically everything was destroyed because of the
perversion of the judges and their compromise in their in their integrity
and everything was for sale and קריה נאמנה. kirya ne'emana. Thank you,
that's the end of it. Okay and only it will only be
restored once we can once again regain our integrity and and judging
justly. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, wait wait so before we leave who
is this רבי יוסי בן אלישע? Rabbi Yossi ben Elisha? I don't
know. That's a good question. I have no idea. I'd have to
look. He'd have to be the son of אלישע. Elisha. I don't
know you'd have to I don't know I didn't check. I don't
know does Steinsaltz sometimes give background? רש"י Rashi acts as background you'd
have to check, I don't know. He's sort of more or less
quoting the פסוק. pasuk. This sort of I guess... No, but he's
using it. I know. I just... well right, I mean he's not
adding so much to the פסוקים psukim except really underscoring them like
we got a lot of פסוקים, psukim, you know, by sort of
highlighting it and saying like this is really, you know, and this
is what all evil comes because of this and we'll only be
restored because of this, right? He certainly gives you know, you know,
focusing on this as the primary message. Right, and with the people's
actions. Right, and there's a lot of פסוקים psukim that talk about
the evil of the people. But the point is he is really
saying no, this is really what it's all about. ואמר עולא ve-amar
Ulla now עולא Ulla said since we're talking about God returning to
Zion אין ירושלים נפדה אלא בצדקה. ein Yerushalayim nifdet ela bi-tzedaka. Jerusalem
will only be redeemed some have the גרסא girsa ישראל, Yisrael, okay,
Israel, the people of Israel. So are we talking about the return
from exile or are we talking about the building of the בית
המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Right, a little unclear but anyway our גרסא girsa
is אין ירושלים נפדה אלא בצדקה ein Yerushalayim nifdet ela bi-tzedaka שנאמר
shenemar ציון, Tzion, Zion, right which is often identified with ירושלים Yerushalayim
במשפט תפדה be-mishpat tipadeh will be redeemed with justice ושביה בצדקה ve-shaveha
bi-tzedaka and those who return to it with צדקה. tzedaka. So the
first part is ציון Tzion is Jerusalem ושביה ve-shaveha is ישראל, Yisrael,
right, so it depends whether he's emphasizing the beginning of the פסוק
pasuk to talk about Jerusalem or the end of the פסוק pasuk
to talk about ישראל, Yisrael, but it comes through justice. Now the
sense in this פסוק pasuk in this is that it only comes
through us in you know embodying and enacting justice. But it's also
used in the context about the issue of whether, you know, when
God brings ultimately the משיח, Mashiach, does he bring it, you know,
because we're deserving or even though we're not deserving? You know, so
there's a famous גמרא Gemara that says the פסוק pasuk says בעתה
אחישנה, be'ita achishena, I will hasten it in its time. So the
גמרא Gemara says make up your mind, if it's in its time
then it's not hastened, if it's hastened it's not in its time.
So it says זכו אחישנה... zakhu achishena... whatever לא זכו בעתה, lo
zakhu be'ita, זכו אחישנה. zakhu achishena. If they are not merit then
it'll come in the appointed time, if they merit it'll be hastened.
But the sense that, you know, to what degree does it come
because of God's compassion, to what degree does it come because we're
deserving? So actually the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon was very מקפיד makpid
because of this גמרא Gemara that in the third ברכה bracha in
בענטשינג Bensching to not say בונה ברחמיו ירושלים אמן boneh ve-rachamav Yerushalayim
amen
because ציון במשפט תפדה. Tzion be-mishpat tipadeh. So we said בונה ירושלים
אמן boneh Yerushalayim amen not ברחמיו. ve-rachamav. So that's interesting, yeah. But
here the question seems less to be a issue of God's justice
and God's mercy or a question about whether we are enacting justice.
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, now said רב פפא, Rav Pappa,
and now we're going to have almost like a one-to-one correspondence between
the types of sort of our sins, particularly the the sins of
the leaders, and how that leads to particular, you know, afflictions. אי
בטלי יהירי, I batli yahiri, if the arrogant ones were to cease,
maybe presumably referring to all lead arrogant leaders, בטלי אמגושי, batli amgushi,
the אמגושי amgushi would be cease. The אמגושי amgushi being being sometimes
translated as magicians, I think that I looked I saw Steinsaltz translate
it as particular as fire priests in, you know, in I'm in
Persia, for Zoroastrian fire priests. דכתיב Dekhtiv ואצרוף כבר סיגיך, ve-etzrof kabor
sigaich, I will remove as with lye your impurities, and here the
word סיגיך sigaich רש"י Rashi says the word סג samekh gimmel can
be like also is is a sense of arrogance. יסגא Yisgeh to
be lift up. Also גס? gas? I skip a line? Okay, we'll
go back. בטלי אמגושי, Batli amgushi, בטלי דייני, batli dayani, if the
judges are are annulled, ceased, meaning the evil judges, the perverted justice
judges as we referred to before, בטלי גזירפתי, batli gizirpati, the גזירפתי
gizirpati will be annulled, which is means apparently non-Jewish you know rulers
or officers that sort of so of the courts. So אי בטלי
יהירי, i batli yahiri, now we're going to show how this correspondence
works. אי בטלי יהירי, I batli yahiri, בטלי אמגושי, batli amgushi, דכתיב
dekhtiv ואצרוף כבר סיגיך, ve-etzrof kabor sigaich, I will remove... remove as
I will cleanse as with lye your impurities, and סיגיך sigayich here
is understood to be like רש"י Rashi says, יסגי yasgi means to
be lifted up like arrogant, also גס. gas. I don't know if
this is intended, but גס gas is, you know, סיג sig and
גס gas is the reverse letters. Anyway, so and the end of
the פסוק pasuk is ואצרף כבור סיגיך, ve'etzrof kabor sigayich, what's the
end of it? We just quoted it before. Where is it? The
end of the פסוק pasuk is ואסירה כל בדיליך. ve'asira kol bedilayich.
And I will remove all בדיליך, bedilayich, so רש"י Rashi says בדיליך
bedilayich are those that separate, so these Zoroastrian fire priests, right, they
cause a separation as it were between ישראל Yisrael and God because
of sort of, you know, their heading a religion that is anti
the sort of monotheism of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Also we know
in other places in the תורה, Torah, in the תורה, Torah, in
the גמרא Gemara that often the Jews were sort of, you know,
were a little bit persecuted particularly on days where there were festivals,
and that they had to contribute to the fire for these fire
for the sacred fire and so on. So it's not exactly clear
why they're being highlighted more than anyone else, but they were seen
as the clear and present sort of antagonists, you know, of what
the Jewish religion at least in בבל. Bavel. Okay, so that's the
first part. And then so that's the ואצרף כבור סיגיך. ve'etzrof kabor
sigayich. איבטלו דייני איבטלו גזירפטי Ibatlei Dayanei, ibatlei Gezirpati and if the
perverted judges are ceased then the גזירפטי, Gezirpati, the non-Jewish
officers will be ceased, דכתיב הסיר ה' משפטיך, dichsiv hesir Hashem mishpatayich,
God will remove your judgment פנה אויבך, pina oyvech, and your enemies
will turn away. So here משפטיך mishpatayich ironically means those that are
judging you in an unjust and perverted way, then your enemies will
be removed. אמר רב אמר רבי מלאי משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון,
Amar Rav, amar Rabbi Milai mishum Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon, מאי
דכתיב, mai dichsiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk שבר ה' מטה
רשעים שבט מושלים. shavar Hashem mateh reshaim shevet moshlim. God will break
the staff of the wicked, the also the staff of the rulers.
So a staff is something that you support yourself on and rely
sort of lean upon, not here's a staff as something you hit
somebody with but it's something that gives support. So שבר ה' מטה
רשעים, shavar Hashem mateh reshaim, God will break the staff of the
wicked, אלו הדיינים, elu hadayanim, the wicked are the judges that judge
as we see for money and unjustly, שנעשו מקל לחזניהם. shenasu makel
lechazzaneihem. Now they are the stick of support for their חזנים, chazzanim,
which means that רש"י Rashi basically says their officers go around and
say to somebody, oh you know you want me to go ahead
and serve these papers? You want me to go ahead and call
somebody to judgment? You want me to go ahead and do what
the judge says? You'll have to sort of pay in order to
get that taken care of. So basically because the, meaning not only
are they to blame, the judges, for their wicked judgment, but they're
to blame because they allow all these other people around them to
rely on their authority, the authority of the judges, and that just
spreads the evil because then they those people that are in all
of these other attendant sort of positions also manage to continue the
perversion and the injustice
as relying on or extending the authority, exploiting the authority of the
judges. Okay, so that's them, that's the חזנים chazzanim as it were,
the officers rely on the authority of the judges. And then שבט
מושלים shevet moshlim and the God will break the staff of the
rulers. אלו תלמידי חכמים, elu talmidei chachamim, these are the Torah sages
שבמשפחות הדיינים, shebemishpachot hadayanim, they're in the family of these judges. What
does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says it means these judges don't
deserve to have their position, they don't know anything, and but what
these people do is that their family members go ahead who are
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim basically teach them enough Torah so that they
can get by so that they can look like they deserve to
be judges or they'll come and they'll defend them when they're doing
something wrong. So all these so they're giving support to these injustices
which are propping them up. Okay, so basically what this is saying
is that if you think about it though, if you combine the
two, ultimately it's the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that are to blame.
The תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are the ones that prop up the
unworthy judges, and the unworthy judges prop up all of the people
that are employed by them and work for them and continue sort
of the
perversion. Enough said. All right,
anyway, so
all right. It also raises issues I guess I'll say it about
questions of what's it called
nepotism and also getting positions, although it's not clear that's what the
גמרא Gemara is referring to, but getting positions because you're in somebody's
family and getting positions. now, because of who you're related to, etcetera.
What?
It did at חיים's Chaim שול. shul.
I know, that's why I made the comment. Okay. מר זוטרא אמר,
Mar Zutra amar, but anyway it's not clear, I mean רש״י Rashi
says it just means that the these people defend them, but it
also could also be that that's also what allows them to have
their position. מר זוטרא אמר אלו
תלמידי חכמים שמלמדים הלכות ציבור לדייני בור. Mar Zutra amar, elu talmidei
chachamim she-melamdim hilchot tzibur le-dayanei bur.
Not necessarily just in your family; these are Torah sages that teach
laws related to the community to ignoramus judges. Meaning these people don't
deserve to be judges, but the, you know, people that know the
law are complicit and give them enough knowledge that they can have
a patina, you know, some type of of an appearance of being
knowledgeable enough that they can pass muster, but ultimately they're ignorant and
it leads to perversion. So what we're also sort of turning to,
you notice, by the way, is from sort of is from is
from
very conscious very, you know, very sort of like intention
I would say from wickedness to space of being right, yeah, right,
like like wickedness to ignorance, meaning to incompetence. Right? So it starts
by people that actually maybe they're competent, but they're just for sale.
And then it moves to people that don't, you know, that don't
deserve the position, but then there's other people that are complicit and
it leads to just as much perversion if you have incompetent people
there and everybody that is helping, you know, you know, implicitly or
explicitly, you know, support that and has a and is in a
position to sort of bring an end to that.
So what are הלכות ציבור?
hilchot tzibur? It means I don't know, it means that they have
positions of authority in the congregation, I think. It doesn't mean it's
opposed to just like because it's more broad, it's not just at
the individual level. All right. So that's the pretty pretty heavy there
condemnation. And now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי אלעזר בן מילאי
משום
ריש לקיש, amar Rabi Elazar ben Milai mishum Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב,
mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? כי כפיכם נגואלו בדם
ואצבעותיכם בעון שפתותיכם דברו שקר לשונכם עולה תהגה, ki chapeichem nigoalu vadam
ve'etzbeoteichem be'avon siftoteichem dibru sheker leshonchem avlah tehgeh, because your hands are
are filled with blood, your fingers with sin, שפתותיכם דברו שקר, siftoteichem
dibru sheker, was that
discussed or not?
Yeah, yeah, me too. Your your lips have spoken falsehood, לשונכם עולה
תהגה, leshonchem avlah tehgeh, your tongues perversion will will talk perversion. כי
כפיכם נגואלו בדם, ki chapeichem nigoalu vadam, now we're going to explain
it. Your hands are like are like, you know, sort of are
like sullied with blood. אלו הדיינים, elu hadayanim, these are the judges,
because the hands mean they stick out a hand for a bribe.
ואצבעותיכם בעון, ve'etzbeoteichem be'avon, and your fingers with sin, אלו סופרי הדיינים,
elu sofrei hadayanim, those that use their fingers basically to write; they
write the judgments, but the judgments are perverted.
שפתותיכם דברו שקר, siftoteichem dibru sheker, your lips speak falsehood, אלו עורכי
הדיינים, elu orchei hadayanim, these are the lawyers. These are these are
the people that that help that help, you know, that help advise
the litigants, which in the גמרא Gemara was seen as something very
inappropriate, right? They're supposed to litigants are just supposed to present their
end their own cases. לשונכם עולה תהגה, leshonchem avlah tehgeh, your tongues
will speak with
perversion, אלו בעלי דינים, elu ba'alei dinim, these are the litigants themselves.
Okay? It's the whole system. The whole system is corrupt. Exactly. The
whole legal system is corrupt. Right. But again, I what's I think
fascinating about this is in addition to the corruptness, I mean first
it's the highlighting that it's the source for all of the evil
of the generation, all the bad things, and the other part is
that it's also it's like it's like it's like who's really to
blame? To some degree, you know, it points the blame at תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim that are propping it up because they're helping defend
or they're helping teach people enough that they need to get by
even though they're incompetent. So תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that basically allow
these judges to be accepted and then it's sort of blaming, right,
everybody that participates in it even if they're not the judge themselves.
And the judge, you know, and every so it's like everybody is
really, you know, is really to blame. Yes, Charlie.
This started out with a תנא tanna and then continued to אמוראים.
Amoraim. Right. So this is something that had to have been a
problem for multiple generations.
Right. You know, it's an interesting question whether when they do this
type of stuff are they, you know, how much is it because
of the immediate מוסר mussar and how much is it like, you
know, like a type of a דרשה drasha on the פסוקים. psukim.
You know what I mean? So sometimes, right, sometimes it's very relevant
to their immediate society and sometimes it's more I don't know, somehow
I do not get the sense the from this text that there's
some like immediate resonance with this. You know, I know, somehow it
seems very abstract.
They're not giving a particular case.
Well, they never it's very rare that they talk, you know, that
they talk in very specifics.
But anyway, I guess what I'm saying is also that I don't,
you know, yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. It's a
good question. Are they motivated to do this because of its relevance
or not? Okay, so now we move on to something very much
unrelated to that, but the same the same the same rabbi.
Why is this here?
It was a digression. We spoke at the end of yesterday about,
you know, רבי יחזקאל Rabbi Yechezkel said to tell us something, right,
tell us something that your father said, which started with the whole
discussion of an אהל ohel on שבת Shabbat and then it led
to it being forgotten and then and then
it leads to different people.
Well, no, I think that then it was just that, well I
guess what's the transition to דורשי רשומות באו עליו? Dorshei Reshumos Bo'u
Olov? How does that come from the idea of the תורה Torah
being forgotten?
It's the woman going from one.
Yeah, I understand. It's a good question. It was not the same
speaker. רבי יוסי בן אלישע Rabbi Yossi ben Elisha was not before.
Yeah, I thought it was just a question... it's a good question
how we moved from the תורה Torah being forgotten
to the perversion of the judges.
Well, this maybe
is its way, but תורה's...
Torah Right, but you don't sort of see that connection to the
exact forgetting of הלכה. halacha. I mean, it's a perversion of הלכה.
halacha. Right, before it was הלכה halacha being forgotten, meaning ignorance, and
here's הלכה halacha being perverted, but it is a good question. There's
not a... I don't see a clear point of connection here.
And I could not find anything on the internet for a רבי
יוסי בן אלישע. Rabbi Yossi ben Elisha.
Oh well, that's it. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so
now we continue with this רב מלאי. Rav Milai. אמר רב מלאי
משום רבי יצחק מגדלאה, Amar Rav Milai mishum Rabbi Yitzchak Migdala'ah, רב
מלאי Rav Milai reported in the name of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
from מגדל, Migdal, מגדלאה. Migdala'ah. מיום שפירש יוסף מאחיו, Miyom sheparash Yosef
me'echav,
from the day that יוסף Yosef separated from his brothers, לא טעם
טעם יין. lo ta'am ta'am yayin. He didn't taste the taste of
wine. דכתיב ולקדקד נזיר אחיו, Dechesiv ulekodkod nezir echav, which is stuck
onto the head of the skull of the one who has separated
from his brothers, but leading, reading literally as נזיר. Nazir. Now of
course it works out well because we know that he had right,
he had the, you know, as the גמרא Gemara emphasizes he had
like this his long hair. He was busy playing with his long
hair, right? So I mean, not exactly in the פסוקים, pesukim, but
anyway, so you combine that with him not drinking wine and he
probably didn't get too close to dead people. So anyway, so there
you go, if he was a נזיר. Nazir. So רבי יוסי בר
חנינא... Rabbi Yose bar Chanina... now presumably he's doing it because he's
in a sense of
like mourning, right? That he's... he's, you know, separated from his family.
But we'll see, I mean, what the significance of this is or
might be. We'll speculate.
Oh man, at least until they came back, this is very stoic.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר אף הם לא טעמו טעם יין. Rabbi
Yose bar Chanina amar af heim lo ta'amu ta'am yayin. They also
didn't drink wine. דכתיב וישתו וישכרו עמו. Dechesiv vayishtu vayishkeru imo. They
drank and they got drunk with him. מכלל דעד האידנא לא. Michlal
de'ad idna lo. And so until now they didn't drink. Now how
do you know that?
Maybe they didn't get drunk maybe.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay, so
anyway... so anyway
the emphasis might be on the עמו, imo, with him. The same
way he had been restraining from wine, they too had been restraining
from wine until that point. So the גמרא... Gemara... ואידך, ve'idach, the
other one says back: שכרות דלא הוי. Shichrus de'lo hava.
They didn't get drunk until that point. שתיה מיהא הוי, Shtiya mi'hava,
but they would drink. Now it's interesting because there's a couple of
interesting things about this. So יוסף Yosef we understand now he feels
he can get drunk because his brothers are back. But his brothers
didn't yet realize it was יוסף. Yosef. So the מהרש"א Maharsha wants
to know, he says, well, maybe it was אימת מלכות. eimas malchus.
They were afraid because he was the king. Because he's also bothered,
how could you say יוסף Yosef was a נזיר? Nazir? What happened,
why he says ויגלח ויחלף שמלתיו? vayigalech vayichalef simlosav? Right? So... so
anyway he wonders whether the גמרא Gemara is literally saying יוסף Yosef
was a נזיר Nazir or just sort of, you know, using that
in a loose way. But there too he says maybe it was
אימת מלכות. eimas malchus. But the interesting question is that like what
is the reason for saying that they did this? Meaning by the
brothers you could understand that it's like they felt bad, it's a
sense of mourning, it's a loss. It's the same idea for יוסף,
Yosef, so point is everybody's feeling bad. That's not normally the sense
one has about this idea of being a נזיר. Nazir. Like, you
know, so the idea of נזיר Nazir is to separate from society
in order to be closer to God. So it's not exactly clear
to me how that theme is playing out here in terms of
the יוסף Yosef and the brothers.
Do you see what people say though? Especially if he's calling you
מנשה Menashe and, you know... Yeah, I understand. אמר רב מלאי. Amar
Rav Milai. So anyway, so רב מלאי Rav Milai also says: בשכר
דראך ושמח בלבו. Bischar de'ra'acha vesamach belibo. Again, these are three unrelated
דרשות drashos or seem to be. In the merit that God foretells
to משה Moshe that אהרן Aharon will see you and rejoice in
his heart, so and the way the מהרש"א Maharsha says not just
sort of seem like he's rejoicing and happy for you. You know,
sometimes you can seem like you're happy for somebody but deep down
you're jealous. But here that he really will rejoice in his heart.
So: זכה לחשן המשפט על לבו. Zacha l'choshen hamishpat al libo. Therefore
he gets to be the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and because and
he will get that חשן משפט choshen mishpat on his heart. You
know, sort of the purity of the heart. So that might be
a little bit contrasting, you know, here the purity on the inside
to what we were sort of just discussing before about the דיינים.
Dayanim. But the גמרא Gemara does not really have, you know, maybe
also a little bit that's the יוסף Yosef theme as well, the
idea of separating from worldly pleasures. But again, it doesn't seem like
they're meant to be thematically connected. It just seems like these are
three statements by the same by the same Rabbi. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara
continues and now that we that was a very interesting aggadic digression.
Now we're back to making an אהל ohel on שבת. Shabbos. But
wasn't it נזיר Nazir before the מלך Melech or Yosef? Okay. Well,
you know, it depends on what... anyway I'm not going to speculate.
שלחו ליה בני בשכר ללוי. Shachlei bnei Bischar de'Levi. So the people
of בשכר Bischar sent to לוי: Levi: אקילא מהו? Akila mahu? What's
the story with an אקילא? Akila? Can we put this canopy up
on our bed on שבת? Shabbos? כשותא בכורמא מהו? Kushuta bekurma mahu?
How about planting hops in a vineyard? Is that a כלאים kilayim
problem? מתיב... meitiv... What happens if somebody dies on יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*? So they had three questions. You know, this idea
of sending שאלות *sheilot* and responsa goes way back. So they sent
it to לוי *Levi*. אדאזיא *Ad'azya*, as the messenger was going to
relay these questions, נח נפשיה דלוי *nach nafshih d'Levi*, Levi had died.
So he wasn't, so who was going to answer the questions? So
אמר שמואל לרב מנשיא *amar Shmuel l'Rav Menashia*, so Shmuel says to
Rav Menashia: אי חכימת שלח להו shlach lehu *i chakimas shalch lehu*,
if you're able, you respond to them. Okay? So maybe he was
a little bit of like, you know, apprenticing him, he said: oh
this question came, you try to answer. So שלח להו shlach lehu
*shalch lehu*, he sent back the following. כילה, חזרנא אכל צידי כילה
ולא מצנא לה צד היתר *Kilah, chazarna akol tzidi kila velo matzana
lah tzad heter*. Regarding the canopy, we looked on all the different
sides of it and we cannot find any way to allow it.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: really? ולשלח להו כדרמי בר יחזקאל
*v'lishlach lehu k'deRami bar Yechezkel*. Why not do like Rami bar Yechezkel
said yesterday in order to have like this string that, you know,
the drawstring? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: לפי שאינם בני תורה
b'nei Torah *lefi she'einam bnei Torah*, because they were not, they were
not really knowledgeable and scholarly, and therefore there was a concern that
if you would tell them, you know, the, that they wouldn't be
able to sort of, you know, attend to these details and nuance.
So if you said: under this circumstance it's allowed, they would come
to, you know, you know, allow it even, even when it should
not be allowed. What a pleasing contrast are we seeing before of
almost about like תלמיד חכם talmid chacham *talmid chacham* perverting a judgment,
you know? And here they're not, he's not saying the exact opposite.
I know, I know. He's not telling them the truth. I know,
I know. So we're going to have, let's go through all case,
all the cases are going to be like this. So let's do
it and then we can talk about it. כשושא בכרמא *Kshusa b'charma*,
so what about, what about, you know, hops in a vineyard? ערבובא
*Irvuva*, that's a mixture, meaning presumably he's saying כלאים *kilayim*. ולשלח להו
כרב טרפון *V'lishlach lehu k'Rav Tarfon*. Why not send like Rav Tarfon?
דתניא *D'tanya*, it says in a ברייתא baraita *braisa*: כשושא, רב טרפון
אומר אין כלאים בכרם וחכמים אומרים כלאים בכרם *Kshusa, Rav Tarfon omer
ein kilayim b'cherem v'chachamim omrim kilayim b'cherem*. Now what's at stake seems
to be whether this is considered to be a vegetable or a
tree. I don't know. Hops is barley, right? So I don't know
why that would be considered, no? What's, what are hops? Hops is
kind of a like an herb, it's kind of like bitter and...
is it like a bush for making beer? It's kind of like
a vine. It's a vine. No, no, no. It's a vine. I
grew up next to hop fields. Okay. So anyway, okay. So that's,
okay. So that's assuming that this is hops. You know, I never
knew exactly the identification. But the issue is is that, is that,
is that, is that grain and vegetation in a vineyard is כלאים
*kilayim*, but trees are not. So the question is like which category
this is in. So רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* says it's not and
חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* say it is. וקיימא לן *V'kaima lan*, and we
have the general ruling: כל המיקל בארץ הלכה halacha כמותו בחוץ לארץ
*kol hameikel ba'aretz halacha kamoso b'chutz la'aretz*. Anybody that has a lenient
position about laws that relate to, you know, like the מצוות התלויות
בארץ *mitzvos hatluyos ba'aretz*, like תרומות, מעשרות, כלאים, ערלה *terumos, maasros, kilayim,
orlah*, those type of agricultural laws, הלכה halacha. כמותו בחוץ לארץ *halacha
kamoso b'chutz la'aretz*. We rule like them in חוץ לארץ *chutz la'aretz*
where it's only rabbinic, or some, some might be הלכה halacha למשה
מסיני *halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai*, but anyway we're lenient in חוץ לארץ *chutz
la'aretz*. So here we should go like רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: לפי שאינם בני תורה bnei Torah *lefi
she'einam bnei Torah*, because they weren't בני תורה Bnei Torah, *bnei Torah*
and therefore he did not give that ruling. So מכריז רב *machriz
Rav*, now Rav made an announcement: האי מאן דבעי למזרע כשושא בכרמא
ליזרע *hai man deba'i lemizra kshusa b'charma lizra*. Anybody who wants to
plant hops in your vineyard can go ahead and plant. He was
not concerned about that. He made this big announcement. Maybe he didn't
make it in this place of, where was this place, בשכר *Bishchar*,
but wherever he made it, he made this announcement. ואמרין חסידא רב
עמרם *v'amrin chasida Rav Amram*, the, the righteous one, מנגיד עלויה *mnagid
ilveia*, would give lashes for people that would do this. Now, so,
so if you take a look, how could he give lashes, literally
lashes? Like he really felt it was a biblical prohibition. So תוספות
Tosfos *Tosafot* says, the little תוספות Tosfos רב עמרם *Tosafot Rav Amram*,
he says: קשיא לי, אמאי? הא קיימא לן הלכה Halakha כרבי טרפון
דמיקל בחוץ לארץ. וצריך לומר דבמקומם לא היו בני תורה Bnei Torah.
*Kashya li, amai? Ha kaima lan halacha k'Rabbi Tarfon d'meikel b'chutz la'aretz.
V'tzarich lomar d'vimkomam lo hayu bnei Torah*. Same thing, that he was
felt that people couldn't be trusted with this knowledge and so much
so that not only that he actually, you know, he actually punished
people that would do it. He was so afraid that they would,
that they would, you know, be irresponsible with this. רב משארשיא יהיב
ליה פרוטה לתינוק נכרי *Rav Mesharshiya yahiv lei pruta l'tinok nochri*. Rav
Mesharshiya gave a dollar, whatever, a quarter to a non-Jewish child וזרע
ליה *v'zara lei*, and he planted. So he didn't do it directly,
he had the non-Jew do it. So presumably he felt that technically
it was permissible, but again he was concerned maybe about, you know,
people, you know, being irresponsible, so he wanted to not do it
directly, have somebody else do it for him. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says: וליתן ליה לתינוק ישראל *v'litein lei l'tinok Yisrael*? So just
have a Jewish kid do it under בר מצוה mitzvah, *Bar Mitzvah*?
אתי למסרך *Ati lemisrach*. No, then he'll come to habituate and come
to do it even when he grows up. וליתן ליה לגדול נכרי
*V'litein lei l'gadol nochri*? Give it to an adult non-Jew? אתי לאחלופי
בישראל *Ati l'achlufi b'Yisrael*. People will think, won't realize maybe he's not
Jewish and they'll come to think that even a ישראל *Yisrael* can
do it. So now, which is very interesting because again, you know,
it sounds like how big of a problem was it? It's just
a problem that people are going to maybe, you know, feeling that
people won't be careful about where the lines are. But maybe that's
what allowed him to do this. Otherwise we have real issues, right,
about hiring people to do for you things that you're not allowed
to do for yourself. Now there is a general debate in הלכה
*halacha*, you know, certainly by שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* there's an issue of
אמירה לגוי amira l'goy *amirah l'goi*, but you know, in what other
areas of הלכה *halacha* do we say that even if you don't
do it directly you can't also hire somebody to do something? doing
for you directly. That's one general question. There's another general question which
is when do we allow a kid to do something or are
we afraid that they'll be habituated to it? תוספות Tosfos raises the
question about can you make קידוש kiddush in a שול shul on
or is it what is it it's yeah like קידוש kiddush in
a שול shul on יום כיפור Yom Kippur wait a minute let
me look at ש"ס shas כוס של ברכה kos shel bracha no
I'm sorry not קידוש kiddush when you have a ברית מילה bris
milah right when you have קידוש kiddush when you have a ברית
מילה bris milah on יום כיפור Yom Kippur right would you do
it on a כוס kos and have a kid drink from it
right so or do we say like a concern about אתי למיסרך?
assi l'mistra? So you know there are these types of questions. Let
me just check what תוספות Tosfos says. Right right I'm sorry right
right so the point is like this so תוספות Tosfos discusses two
contrasting cases. One is you have a ברית מילה bris milah on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur can you make it על הכוס al hakos
and have a kid drink? And the other is when saying שהחיינו
shehecheyanu on יום כיפור Yom Kippur there's a discussion in the גמרא
Gemara can you say שהחיינו shehecheyanu על הכוס? al hakos? We say
שהחיינו shehecheyanu right at the beginning of יום כיפור Yom Kippur can
you say it על הכוס al hakos not exactly make קידוש kiddush
but say it על הכוס al hakos and have a kid drink?
So תוספות Tosafos says well maybe the first case
is better than the second because the first case is just is
very rare and as opposed to doing it as a regular thing
each year
that will lead
to habituating and that
will lead to you know people becoming practiced you know developing this
practice which ultimately will lead to doing something wrong in the future.
But anyway these are very like interesting more general questions. Number one
is hiring somebody a non-Jew to do something for you that you're
not allowed to do when is it allowed or not this אמירה
לגוי when does it apply outside of הלכות שבת? hilchos Shabbos? And
the other is having a kid do something you know and what
to degree that it's the חינוך chinuch questions and habituating and so
on. So these are two very broad issues and here they're being
brought to bear on this much narrower on this much
more sort of you know less weighty issue of something which is
seen to be from the גמרא Gemara technically allowed but just a
concern that it will that people won't be responsible with that. We're
not allowed to hire non-Jew to do ממש כלאים mamash kilayim right
right ממש כלאים?
mamash kilayim? Right no so now the גמרא Gemara continues so that's
number two so number two also has to do with the issue
about being about misusing the about being irresponsible and as I said
then questions about sort of playing with that in cases where some
rabbis weren't concerned some were some split the difference and had a
non-Jew or non-Jewish child do it and so on. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this okay שלח להו now how about the
third one? מת meis so somebody dies on יום טוב Yom Tov
so שלח להו he sent them מת לא יתעסקו בו לא יהודים
ולא ארמאים. meis lo yisasku bo lo yehudim v'lo aramaim. If somebody
dies on יום טוב Yom Tov neither Jews nor non-Jews can involve
themselves in the burial. לא ביום טוב ראשון ולא ביום טוב שני
lo b'Yom Tov rishon v'lo b'Yom Tov sheni not on the first
day יום טוב Yom Tov or the second day. גמרא Gemara says
איני eini is that true? ואמר רב יהודה בר שילת אמר רב
אסי עובדא הוה בבי כנישתא דמעון v'amar Rav Yehuda bar Shilas amar
Rav Assi uvda hava b'vei knishta d'Maon so there's a case in
the synagogue of מעון Maon ביום טוב הסמוך לשבת b'Yom Tov hasamuch
l'Shabbos it was יום טוב Yom Tov after שבת Shabbos ולא ידענא
אם לפניה אם לאחריה v'lo yadana im lifneha im l'achareha and I
don't know if it was יום טוב Yom Tov before שבת Shabbos
or after. If it was before שבת Shabbos then not burying on
יום טוב Yom Tov would lead to just multiple days you know
that he wouldn't be buried. Now he's not buried on יום טוב
Yom Tov and on שבת Shabbos and it'll be like two three
days. If it's יום טוב Yom Tov after שבת Shabbos and he's
already not been buried for one day presumably the case would have
been he died on שבת Shabbos so we're already getting to the
fact that he's you know that that it's really quite delayed but
either way ואתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן v'asu lakamei d'Rabbi Yochanan they came
before רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ואמר להו יתעסקו בו עממי v'amar lehu
yisasku bo amamim let non-Jews bury him. ואמר רבא v'amar Rava and
רבא Rava says מת ביום טוב ראשון יתעסקו בו עממי ביום טוב
שני יתעסקו בו ישראל meis b'Yom Tov rishon yisasku bo amamim b'Yom
Tov sheni yisasku bo Yisrael if somebody dies on the first day
יום טוב Yom Tov he can be buried by non-Jews on the
second day יום טוב Yom Tov even buried by Jews ואפילו ביום
טוב שני של ראש השנה v'afillu b'Yom Tov sheni shel Rosh Hashanah
even the second day of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah which normally is
weighty is we give it the same weight as the first day
of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah but for the הלכה of מת meis
he can be buried even by Jews on the second day ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah מה שאין כן בביצה matshkein b'beitzah which we wouldn't
say like an egg born on the first day is still אסור
assur the second day we normally treat first and second day יום
טוב Yom Tov as the same but not for this הלכה. So
you see that either non-Jews or Jews can bury based on first
day or second day. So the גמרא Gemara says לפי שאינן בני
תורה lefi she'ein b'nei Torah again they're not בני תורה they cannot
be trusted with that knowledge. So that raises so I want to
say two things and then we can talk about לפי שאינן בני
תורה lefi she'ein b'nei Torah for a minute which is number one
רש"י Rashi seems to say that this idea of burying on first
day יום טוב Yom Tov second day יום טוב Yom Tov. is
only in a case like the גמרא Gemara just said that it's
סמוך לשבת samuch l'Shabbos where it's not where it's actually being extended
even by more days because of שבת Shabbos. but that's not the
פסק psak the הלכה really is is that regardless of סמוך לשבת
samuch l'Shabbos or not you know מת ביום טוב ראשון meis b'Yom
Tov rishon bury by non-Jews יום טוב שני Yom Tov sheni even
by Jews. There's a question to what degree this applies nowadays where
you can refrigerate you know the body which we do and there's
not that same urgency. Interestingly תוספות also brings an interesting discussion where
תוספות says that he quotes a גמרא Gemara that says that we're
concerned about like the you know sort of non-Jews that they would
that they see us burying our מת *meis* on the second day
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, then they'll come to press us
into service for other things. They'll say, look, you Jews are prepared
to do things on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. So תוספות
*Tosafos* says like this, גם יש לירא *gam yesh lera*, five lines
from the bottom of the תוספות יום טוב Yom Tov, *Tosafos Yom
Tov*. He says like the middle of the line, line starts with
the word כיון *kivan*. He says, גם יש לירא פן יצוו השרים
להתעסק במלאכתם ולכתוב מה שהם רוצים *gam yesh lera pen yitzavu hasarim
le'isasek b'milachtam velichtov mah shem rotzim*. We're afraid that if they see
us doing work on יום טוב Yantiv שני *Yom Tov sheini*
even for the
sake of the dead, they'll press us into their service and make
us do stuff for them. ושלח ליה רבינו תם *v'shalach lei Rabbeinu
Tam*, so
this was a case, I'm sorry, it started earlier. I should have
said the first end of the going up, the middle of the
last wide line. ומעשה היה והוליכו מת חוץ לתחום ביום טוב והלכו
אחריו בסוסים להתעסק במת וכעס רבינו תם אף על ההולכים ברגל בלא
סוסים *Umaiseh hava v'holichu meis chutz latchum b'Yom Tov, v'halchu achrav b'susim
le'isasek b'meis. V'ka'as Rabbeinu Tam af al ha'holchim beragel belo susim*. So
there was a case that they buried somebody on יום טוב Yantiv
*Yom Tov* and some people rode out to bury him, and some
people just walked, and רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* was angry even about
them. And at the end he says, ושלח ליה רבינו תם *v'shalach
lei Rabbeinu Tam*, back to the end of תוספות *Tosafos*, בני בשכר
אינם בני תורה בני מליון בני תורה *B'nei Biscar einam b'nei Torah,
B'nei Million b'nei Torah*? So he basically applied the same principle. He
said, hey, if they had to say in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that they couldn't do in בשכר *Biscar* because they wouldn't trust them,
so you guys also, this city also, they're not בני תורה *b'nei
Torah* and therefore they cannot follow this הלכה *halacha*. So two reasons
not to follow that הלכה *halacha*. One is maybe in practice it'll
lead to negative consequences, we'll be pressed into service by the non-Jews,
and the other is the same reason of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
applying this issue of בני תורה *b'nei Torah*. So this raises really
important questions about about פסקנינג *paskening*. You know, how much there is
a reality, I'll start with this. Look, I think for many of
us, this strikes us as very paternalistic and not respecting people's being
sort of just responsible for themselves and they're asking you a הלכה
*halacha*, you give them a פסק *psak*, and if, treat them as
adults and let them decide and so on. The reality is is
that there definitely people who, the most well-intentioned people, but you know
that as soon as you sort of say that okay, this is
the הלכה *halacha* but בדיעבד B'diavad, *bedieved*, in this case, in this
case, this is the הלכה בדיעבד B'diavad *halacha bedieved*, that בדיעבד *bedieved*
becomes the לכתחילה L'chatchila, *l'chatchila*. You know, or you know that there's
some people who won't be able to totally internalize the difference and
actually will, if this is okay, they'll come to think the other
thing is okay as well. That's a reality, that is how people
will act. So the question becomes, how much is that the rabbi's
responsibility? Because ultimately is a person just asking you for the הלכה
*halacha*? Or is the person actually asking you, tell me something that's
going to keep me on the right side of the law? So
if they're really saying tell me something that's going to keep me
on the right side of the law, then you have to tell
them something that might not even exactly be technically what the הלכה
*halacha* is because they're asking you for helping them to keep within
הלכה *halacha*. It's a real challenge I think. It's interesting that the
way some of these handbooks deal with it, these הלכה *halachic* handbooks
deal with it, is they have the stuff, the footnotes and the
main text. The main text is in English, and then in the
footnotes you have all of the distinctions and all the nuances because
they figure anybody that can read the footnotes can handle it. The
problem is is that in ישראל *Israel* it doesn't work because everybody
can read the footnotes. But you have to maybe
have the patience to read the footnotes. Anyway, but it's, look, I
do, this is an issue that you do find in the פוסקים
*poskim* that there is a discussion about can you always exactly teach
the exact letter of the law if the reality is is that
people will not be able to follow it as it is taught
and how much are they asking you just for the information or
are they
essentially asking: A, how much are they asking you to help keep
them on the right side of the law? And B, how much
is it your responsibility? So I think it raises very important questions.
Well and I would also say that there's a distinction between the
first two cases and the last. Like the first two cases no
one has to actually plant your whatever it is or hops in,
he plants it somewhere else, not a big deal.
Okay, there might be economic reasons.
Right, no, but what I'm saying is though, on the last case
there's the competing value of כבוד המת *kevod hameis*, which is now
you're telling somebody to let the body decompose a little longer.
That's a very good point.
And that's a much bigger problem with that last case.
Right, the first cases are just issues of like, alright. I hear
that, the competing value here is very serious. Yes, true.
I was warned when I started the conversion not to trust any
הלכה *halachic* handbook because of some of the issues you mentioned.
Right, right. Because they're too מחמיר *machmir*.
They're too מחמיר *machmir*. They're too מחמיר *machmir*, and they represent the
particular opinion of the person who wrote it for the particular audience
for whom it's being written. You particularly
warned me against the קיצור שלחן ערוך *Kitzur Shulchan Aruch*, which doesn't
even have footnotes. Right, right.
I mean, look, I do think it's an issue. I mean I
think there's a problem which is when you just assume that nobody
can be trusted or whatever as opposed to responding to a particular...
right, that's patronizing, as opposed to like responding to a very particular
circumstance where you know the individual, but I don't know. Yeah, רבקה
*Rifka*.
This whole controversy around רוט קלדרון *Ruth Calderon's* and her wonderful תלמוד
*Talmud* lecture she gave in the כנסת *Knesset* and many... Saying this
is terrible because she announced now Talmud is open to everybody.
Oh my God, God forbid, what's going to happen if everybody learns
גמרא? Gemara Yes.
And that's just tragic that people who are not observant get to...
I know but that's a different issue than this. We can discuss
that but that's a different issue
than the fact that it is available to everyone, including the non-observant.
Right.
Rabbi Steinsaltz had
the same same issue, right, when you don't tell them, they ask
the question, don't give them the real answer because maybe they'll mix
it up.
Right, right, it's trying to protect the knowledge, right, to
keep the knowledge in the hands... right.
I
do think there are differences because there it's not about
observance and non-observance but it is an issue about trying to protect
knowledge. That's true. You know, keep people in and keep people out.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, very fascinating digressions there. אמר
רב אבין בר רב הונא אמר רב חמה בר גוריה: Amar Rav
Avin bar Rav Huna amar Rav Chama bar Guria: מתעטף אדם בכילה
Mis'atef adam bikila back to making an אהל ohel on שבת. Shabbos
I bet you never expected that making an אהל ohel on שבת
Shabbos, would be so fascinating. So a person can wrap himself with
the canopy sheet. You can't use the canopy sheet to make a
canopy on שבת, Shabbos but you can use it as a טלית
tallis and wrap yourself with it ובקיסכסיה u-vikiskas'ha
and with its straps. The straps would be used just to strap
it onto the bed. ויוצא לרשות הרבים בשבת V'yotzei l'reshus harabim b'Shabbos
and wear it in רשות הרבים reshus harabim even though it has
straps and the straps are not really part and
don't function as part of the garment, they're there to use it
for the canopy, it's considered to be secondary to the garment and
since you're wearing it as a garment, it's not a problem. Like
I can wear my blanket out. ואינו חושש V'eino choshesh yeah if
it has four corners you have to worry about ציצית. tzitzis. מאי
שנא Mai shna says the גמרא Gemara מדדרב הונא? mi-deRav Huna? דאמר
רב הונא אמר רב היוצא בטלית שאינה מצוייצת כהלכתה בשבת חייב חטאת.
De-amar Rav Huna amar Rav ha-yotzei b'tallis she'eina metzuyetzes k'hilchasa b'Shabbos chayav
chatas. If somebody goes out with a טלית tallis on שבת Shabbos
that doesn't have ציצית tzitzis on all four corners, let's say it
has them on two or three corners, then you're חייב chayav a
sin offering because you're carrying the ציצית. tzitzis. The ציצית tzitzis that
are now not doing the מצוה, mitzvah so they're not incorporated into
the בגד, beged, so they're just strings that are not part of
the בגד beged at this stage, so you're carrying them. So this
too you should be carrying your straps. So the גמרא says: ציצית
לגבי טלית חשיבי ולא בטלי. Tzitzis legabei tallis chashivi velo batli. ציצית
Tzitzis vis-a-vis the טלית tallis are significant on their own right and
they're not considered to be like just secondary and sort of a
part of it. הני לא חשיבי ובטלי. Hani lo chashivi batli. These
straps are not significant. So רש"י Rashi says the reason ציצית tzitzis
are more significant is because they have תכלת techeiles and therefore they're
expensive and so on. תוספות says they're significant just because they're a
מצוה mitzvah object and because either if you're not going to use
them on this טלית, tallis, you'll remove them and use them on
something else. So they do have something as an independent thing in
itself, whereas the strap is only sort of a part of the
בגד. beged. You don't see the strap as, oh, I'm going to
salvage that strap, I'll use that strap somewhere else, and therefore since
it's only a part of the בגד beged and you're wearing the
בגד, beged, the straps are not considered to be something that's being
carried by the בגד, beged, it's just considered part of the בגד.
beged.
Yes. What about wearing a טלית tallis shawl at night or walking
home when there's no מצוה mitzvah, to...?
That's a good question. Whether it's defined by the actual חפצא chefza
of the טלית tallis or the קיום kiyum of the מצוה, mitzvah
so it's actually a good question. Yeah, it's somewhat debated about, so
it's a good question. I'm not going to answer but it's a
good question. You're right, whether you have to be מקיים mekayem the
מצוה once you say no it's incorporated into the בגד beged it
doesn't matter because it's a בגד beged with ציצית. tzitzis. Okay so
גמרא says: אמר רבה בר רב הונא מערים אדם על המשמרת ביום
טוב. Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna maarim adam al hamishmeres b'Yom Tov.
Going back to now enough of אהל, ohel, now going back to
the other point of the משנה, Mishnah, which is about using a
משמרת mishmeres to pour wine through. So we said that there was
a debate about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim whether
you can put this משמרת mishmeres on the vessel on יום טוב.
Yantiv Everybody agrees if it's on, you can use it on יום
טוב. Yantiv Again יום טוב Yantiv where you can do things related
to food. So he says if you פוסק pasken like the חכמים
which we do that you can't put it on יום טוב, Yantiv
but you can scheme and get it on the vessel. How do
you do? מערים אדם על המשמרת ביום טוב לתלות בה רימונים. Maarim
adam al hamishmeres b'Yom Tov litlos bah rimonim. You put the משמרת
mishmeres on top of the vessel and you say, oh, I'm doing
it because I want to, like suspend a pomegranate on top of
the vessel and I'm using this as a lid. Okay,
so and that's why you're putting it there, to put pomegranates in
it, that's what you say, not in order to... and then it's
not עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. רש"י Rashi points out since we said
the concern here was not אהל, ohel, the concern because it was
just a vessel, the concern was עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. עובדא דחול
Uvda d'chol is that you're going you're sort of doing
this very labor-intensive type of a process of sifting.
So it's a type of activity that you do in a weekday.
Okay but here you're not you're saying, oh I'm not doing it
for sifting, I'm just doing it to put a pomegranate on it
so it's no longer עובדא דחול uvda d'chol and therefore
once you have it up, דתלא בה שמרין d'tala bah shamrim and
then once it's up, then you can use it for putting the
wine lees in it and to do the sifting of the wine
because so... אמר רב אשי והוא דתלא בה רימונים. Amar Rav Ashi
v'hu d'tala bah rimonim. No, no,
okay, that's fine but you can't just say you're doing it for
pomegranate, you have to actually use it for pomegranates so that it
looks a little bit more kosher. So the גמרא says: מאי שנא
מהא דתניא Mai shna me-ha detanya how's it different from that which
we taught in the... how's it different than that which we taught
in the ברייתא baraita מטילים שכר במועד לצורך המועד matilim sheichar bemoed
letzorech hamoed you can make a beer a mead on יום טוב
Yantiv for the purpose of יום טוב Yom Tov but שלא לצורך
המועד אסור shelo letzorech hamoed asur but if you're doing it for
after יום טוב Yom Tov, it's אסור asur אחד שכר תמרים ואחד
שכר שעורים echad sheichar tamarim ve'echad sheichar se'orim whether it is mead
of dates or whether it's like mead of barley beer אף על
פי שיש להם ישן af al pi sheyesh lahem yashan even if
you have old stuff you can make new stuff for יום טוב
מערים maarim you can trick ושותה מן החדש veshoteh min hachadash and
say you know you're doing it for drinking you want to drink
the new stuff even if you have available old stuff you can
do it on יום טוב so how is it different than that
case now I don't exactly see why it's different there you're tricking
the simple sense of that ברייתא is that you not only are
making the beer you actually are drinking the beer so it's just
like it you say you're doing it for this purpose and then
you go out and you actually have to employ it in that
purpose you have to use it for the pomegranates you have to
drink the beer but it seems like the גמרא is reading that
the מערים ושותה מן החדש maarim veshoteh min hachadash means you can
claim you're doing it to drink from the new stuff even if
you're not that's at least how the גמרא seems to be reading
it so the גמרא says התם לא מוכח מילתא hastham lo mocha
milsa no there it's not obvious because there people don't know you
have old beer so people see you making beer they'll assume you're
making beer because you want to drink the beer on יום טוב
there's nothing obviously wrong הכא מוכח מילתא hacha mocha milsa here if
you don't put the pomegranate in it it looks like you're putting
this sieve on in order to sift wine and you're not supposed
to put on a sieve interesting you can sift wine on יום
טוב but you're not supposed to put on the sieve well let's
just see a couple more cases about this אמרו ליה רבנן לרב
אשי amru lei rabbanan le'Rav Ashi so the rabbis said to רב
אשי Rav Ashi חזי מר האי צורבא מרבנן chazi mar hai tzurva
merabbanan did you see that sort of young rabbi or rabbinic student
רב הונא בר חייא שמיה Rav Huna bar Chiya shemei his name
is רב הונא בר חייא Rav Huna bar Chiya ואמרי לה רב
הונא בר רב חלבו שמיה ve'amrei lei Rav Huna bar Rav Chalvo
shemei and some say רב הונא בר רב חלבו שמיה Rav Huna
bar Rav Chalvo shemei דשקיל ברדא דתומא deshakil barda detuma he took
a piece of like a head of a garlic not a head
a what's it called a clove of garlic ומנח בדבי ברזא דדנא
umanach devei barza dedanna and he put it in a faucet of
a barrel to like stop up the faucet okay I wouldn't want
to drink the wine after that clove of garlic ואמר לאתנויי קא
מכווני ve'amar le'atnoei ka michavne and he
said oh I'm just doing it as a place to store my
garlic okay
as opposed to and probably he was really doing to stop up
the barrel and that somehow was somehow problematic not exactly clear why
or how problematic it was but okay anyway so you see he's
tricking
רש"י Rashi says it's like מתקן metaken but you know again maybe
it was a hole that shouldn't have been there in the barrel
normally the ברזא barza means like the faucet but anyway somehow he
was fixing the barrel but he was claiming he was just putting
his garlic away and another thing he did
ואזל וניים במעברא ve'azal venayam be'mabra and he went
and he took a nap on a boat not a bridge a
what's it
called like a raft yeah but what's that like a flat board
almost anyway yeah raft anyway Huck Twain
anyway some type of a thing raft that was used for crossing
the river it was like a okay so it was a
raft במעברא be'mabra ואמר ליה לאחישא ve'amar lei l'achissa and basically the
non-Jew who was you know it was a ferry and the non-Jew
you know went to the other side but he was asleep when
it was happening oh and then he got to the other side
he woke up וסייר פירי vesiyar peirei and he used the opportunity
to go check out his fruit on the other side of the
river okay and he
said אנא לנייום קא מכווני ana leniyum ka michavne I was just
going to sleep there I can't be held responsible that he happened
to take me across the river so anyway so they were really
wanted רב אשי Rav Ashi to do something about this guy he
was like playing all these tricks אמר להו amar lehu he said
to the students הערמה קאמרתו harama ka'amartu what just like tricking scheming
הערמה דרבנן היא harama de'rabbanan hi
it's just a type of scheming with you know with rabbinic problems
none of this is biblical and he's doing it in a way
that you know obviously his intent is one thing but on the
surface it looks okay and so therefore that type of thing צורבא
מרבנן לא אתי למעבד לכתחילה tzurba merabbanan lo asi leme'evad lechatchila and
once again we get this defining this class making the whole thing
about class somebody who's a תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham he'll know enough
that he'll do it in this way this like
this בני תורה essentially he'll be able to do it in this
way that looks good on the surface and he won't come to
do it that way like to blatantly violate to violate in a
way that's actually prohibited now obviously there's two problems here besides the
repeating of the theme before that we can trust certain people and
not other people there's the other issue which is why is הערמה
harama מותר mutar anyway forget that it won't lead to doing it
in the improper way you know what's the whole concept about sort
of doing it you know technically you're claiming you're doing it for
another purpose you know now in some way you can look at
it as a way of trying to balance the idea which is
what הלכה is always trying to balance which is the issues about
like how do you have like a certain law which you feel
is you know the proper law on the other side be sensitive
to the human need to do certain things and that the law
becomes too restrictive so sometimes it translates to לכתחילה, בדיעבד, or שעת
הדחק. Sha'as Had'chak. So this seems to be one of the safety
valves almost is, okay, it's אסור, Asur, but under certain circumstances if
you fake it and make it look כשר, Kosher, that'll be כשר.
Kosher. But the question is, I find this more disturbing than all
those other things because this is sort of teaching about the principle
of how to pretend,
how to get around the law. It sort of seems like the
ethos of הערמה Ha'arama here is much more problematic than just saying
like בדיעבד or שעת הדחק Sha'as Had'chak type of an approach.
Yeah Charlie, even the word הערמה Ha'arama is the worst.
It's the worst, הערמה, Ha'arama, right.
We didn't have this concern about whether סתם הקנקן Sitam Hakankan when
we were talking about the hammer and the walnut.
A hammer and walnut is not הערמה. Ha'arama. What do you mean?
That's you use a כלי Kli which is normally מוקצה Muktzah but
if you want to use it to crack open a walnut.
No, no, that's not override. That's not הערמה. Ha'arama. That is
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור Kli shemelachto l'issur is מותר לצורך גופו. Mutar l'tzorech
gufo. That's not a הערמה. Ha'arama. But you know, the big הערמה,
Ha'arama, we're coming up to פסח. Pesach. The big הערמה Ha'arama is
the whole selling of all of your חמץ. Chametz. Now they say
that's דרבנן D'rabbanan because also like you do ביטול Bitul so ביטול
Bitul really works דרבנן. D'rabbanan. There's a question if you could really
do ביטול Bitul when you're in a business and you own hundreds
of thousands of dollars. But anyway, but the fact that we use
הערמה, Ha'arama, it is a principle, and the גמרא here, we've had
it a few times already in מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbos, does not
seem to be bothered by it. Like it seems to sometimes ask
exactly what are the parameters. You might remember before there's another case
about צער בעלי חיים. Tza'ar ba'alei chayim. There were questions about what
are the parameters that we allow here. It seems to be like
oh, as long as you're a תלמיד חכם and we can trust
you, you can do any דרבנן D'rabbanan and you can sort of
do בהערמה. B'ha'arama. All right, which is right.
And exactly, who is the הערמה? Ha'arama? So the הערמה Ha'arama I
would say is not to G-d, but it's to sort of it's
to give no, the הערמה Ha'arama sort of gives acknowledgment,
respect, but more than respect, just sort of acknowledges what the law
is. It's sort of saying that you're sort of acknowledging yes, that
there is this law here in place. But on the other hand,
so it's better than like frontally violating and not acknowledging the force
of the law. But the problem is is that it teaches a
whole approach about scheming and sneaking. So I don't know, I don't
know what the answer to it is besides the other theme that
we already had, which is the בני תורה, non-בני תורה. Let's start
the next topic. משנה: Mishna: נותנין מים על גבי שמרים בשביל שיצולו.
Notnin mayim al gabei shemarim bishvil sheyeitzolu. You can put water if
you have lees lees of grapes, you can pour water through it
so the water, and it's in a sieve, the water gets the
flavor of the grapes and goes through. It's basically like a tea
bag. Okay, the water goes through, gets the flavor and comes out.
So that's not sifting, because water comes in and water, it's not
like a mixture goes into a sieve and is separated. Water comes
in, gets the flavor and then goes out through the sieve. So
that's not an issue of בורר. Borer. That's okay. That's why you
can, בישול Bishul issues aside, that's why you can use a tea
bag on שבת Shabbos, and it's not a type of a
בורר. Borer. ומסננין את היין בסודרין. U'mesanenin es hayayin besudarim. Now even
if you have wine that has impurities, although you cannot use this
formal sort of sieve that you put on the top of this
vessel, that you can't do on שבת, Shabbos, but you can use
some non-normal כלי. Kli. You can use it with a piece of
cloth and use that as a sieve for your wine.
Why is it not בורר? Borer? ובכפיפה מצרית U'v'chfiffa mitrit or with
like a type
of a basket, a wicker basket which can serve as a sieve,
a non-normal
כלי. Kli. ונותנין ביצה במסננת של חרדל. V'notnin beitzah bimshenenes shel chardal.
You can also pass an egg through a mustard sieve because it
has the yellow from the mustard. So by passing the egg through,
either the egg gets the yellow color and you want the egg
to be yellowed, or the egg or the yolk is going into
the mustard below and it's adding yellow to the mustard mixture. Now
all of these are questions as why is this not בורר? Borer?
Okay, ועושין אנומלין בשבת. V'osin anomilin b'Shabbos.
You can make אנומלין Anomilin on שבת, Shabbos which is a certain
type
of a mixture. How do they describe it there?
Wine mixed with honey.
There you go. Okay, some type of right of flavored wine, honey
wine. רבי יהודה אומר בשבת בכוס. Rabbi Yehuda omer b'Shabbos bekos. On
שבת Shabbos, you can make it in a vessel, in a כוס.
Kos. You can't make a large amount. ביום טוב בלוגין. B'yom tov
belogin. On יום טוב you can make it in a לוג, Log,
like a much larger container. במועד בחבית. B'moed b'chavis. And on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed you can even make it in a barrel. Okay,
so how much are you allowed to make based on שבת, Shabbos
יום טוב, or חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. רבי צדוק אומר הכל לפי
האורחין. Rabbi Tzadok omer hakol lefi ha'orchin. It all depends on how
many guests you have. Okay, let's just go a little bit like
three, two or three more lines. אמר זעירי: Amar Zeiri: נותן אדם
יין צלול ומים צלולים לתוך המשמרת בשבת ואינו חושש. Notin adam yayin
tzalul umayim tzululim letoch hamishmeres b'Shabbos v'eino choshesh. You can put clear
wine and clear water into a sieve for שבת Shabbos and you
don't have to worry. This is why you can use a water
filter on שבת because if it's clear and you would have drunk
it anyway, but you prefer that it be even more sifted, but
it's fit to be drunk the way it is, that's not considered
a problem of sifting or
of filtering, I should say filtering. We'll talk about that. אבל עכורין
לא. Aval achurin lo. But if it's cloudy, no. מיתיבי. Meisivi. I'll
ask you on this: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר טורד אדם חבית
של יין ויין ושמריה ונותן לתוך המשמרת בשבת. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel
omer tored adam chavis shel yayin veyayin ushemareha venoten letoch hamishmeres b'Shabbos.
You
You could actually actively mix up your wine with the lees on
שבת *Shabbos*, even though those lees have settled in the bottom, and
put it through a sieve and then you'll and have and do
the sifting on שבת *Shabbos*. Even though you're actively mixing it up,
now nobody presumably, besides that you're actively doing it, nobody presumably wants
to drink the wine with the lees, so why is that allowed?
That's עכורין *achurin*, that's cloudy. And he says תרגמא זעירי בין הגתות
שנו *Targema Zeiri bein ha-gittos shanu*.
That's between the periods of the of the pressing of the wine
press, meaning this was a time when the wine was settling, so
people actually at this time of the year would be okay drinking
it when it was cloudy. So what the גמרא *Gemara* actually says
here is an amazing thing. If you can drink liquid the way
it is, or it's a time of year whatever that it's drunk
in this way, even though it has impurities, you're allowed to filter
it. Now, first of all, that's wild because we never say that
by normal בורר *borer*. We never say you can pick out things,
you know, let's say you know, if you were to have eaten
it without picking out the stuff, you can pick out the stuff.
We never say that. For some reason when we deal with when
we deal with filtering liquids, it's different than normal food. Okay, there's
a whole discussion in the אחרונים *achronim* and the ראשונים *rishonim* why
that is, but that's a huge difference, number one. Number two, it's
basically liquid versus solids. Now, but the הלכה *halacha* is that if
most people would drink this liquid the way it is and you
would drink it the way it is, you're allowed to use a
filter, which is why you can use a filter on your water.
However, if as Michael said, you're concerned about the copepods and you
won't drink water unfiltered, you cannot use the filter on שבת *Shabbos*,
you actually have to prepare filtered water from before שבת *Shabbos*, because
you would refuse to eat it without it being filtered. Okay, but
for example, things like orange juice and pulp, if you're prepared if
most people will drink it that way and you're prepared to drink
it that way, רב משה *Rav Moshe* says it's fine. For some
reason רב שלמה זלמן *Rav Shlomo Zalman* says you can't, he tries
to make a distinction with the pulp case which I don't really
understand, but I do understand, but anyway, but I think רב משה
*Rav Moshe*'s is the more simple approach. How about also if you've
got a pitcher that has the like teeth in it to keep
the ice out? Right? So first of all, so you might so
you might say ice and water is really the same thing, it's
not even, but anyway, but also most people presumably would drink it
with the ice, right? So again, this is really important in terms
of the issues of liquids has a different principle than the issues
of solids and if it could be drunk the way it is,
there's actually not a problem to filtering it on שבת *Shabbos*, at
least if you use a, the question is about using at least
here we're talking about like a maybe a non-standard vessel, what about
a standard vessel that's you know maybe the other issue, but anyway,
this is very this is very relevant להלכה *le-halacha* and we will
continue with the גמרא *Gemara*.